Guide to the Vicki Hearne Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, 1969-2001; Series II; 13.14; (32 boxes)
  - Articles and Presentations
    - "A Bar of Soap, or How toTell a Medical Horror Story," draft, typescript, corrected, with holograph byline, undated (Box 15, Folder 196)
    - "Baubles, Bangles, and Beads: The Most Detested Art," two drafts, typescript (photocopy), corrected, 1997, 1998 (Box 15, Folder 197)
    - "Beastly Behaviors," multiple drafts with varying titles, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 198-199)
    - "The Beautiful Hybrid," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 200)
    - "Between the Poem and the Treatise," "draft of introduction to: A Collect for Philosophers," drafts, typescript (original and photocopy), undated (Box 15, Folder 201)
    - "Beware of the Dog!" draft, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 202)
    - "Beware of the Dog: Thurber, Rex, and the Making of a Hero," printed version, published in Harper's Magazine, 1986 February (Box 15, Folder 203)
    - "Beware of the Dog: Thurber's Philosophy of Animal Consciousness," draft, typescript, corrected, laid into note pad containing related notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 204)
    - "Calling Animals by Name," printed version, published in Esquire, Japanese edition, 1992 April (Box 15, Folder 205)
    - "The Case of the Fallen Jockey, the Capitoline Bulldog, [And Lord Pigott] (How Lassie Got Her Head)," draft, typescript, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 206)
    - "The Companion Animal: A Modern Quest for the Hearth," two drafts, typescript (original and photocopy), 1989, undated (Box 15, Folder 207)
    - "Constitutional Kindness," draft, typescript, with holograph notes, 1989 (Box 15, Folder 208)
    - "The Cruelty Question," printed version, published in the Los Angeles Times Magazine, 1988 December 11 (Box 15, Folder 209)
    - "The Disobedient Orangutan," holograph notes in notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 210)
    - "The Dog Bite," draft, typescript, 1988 (Box 15, Folder 211)
    - "The Dog Trainer's Technique of Knowing Mind," draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 15, Folder 212)
    - "The Domain of Reference," draft, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 213)
    - "Domestic, Tame, Feral, and Wild," draft, holograph in notebook, undated (Box 15, Folder 214)
    - "The Domestication of Philosophy," two drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 16, Folder 215)
    - "Dreaming Poetry," draft, typescript (photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 16, Folder 216)
    - "The Effects of Clever Hans," draft, typescript, undated (Box 16, Folder 217)
    - "Game Dog Last and Final," draft, typescript, 1993 (Box 16, Folder 218)
    - "Honest on Purpose," draft, typescript, undated (Box 16, Folder 219)
    - "Horses in Partnership with Time," three drafts, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 16, Folder 220)
    - "How to Tell a Dog Story: The Dilemmas of Animals and Public Policy," ("Austin/Dallas talk"), draft, typescript, 1992 (Box 16, Folder 221)
    - "In Memoriam, William Koehler, 1914-1993," draft, holograph, with copy of Koehler's death certificate (Box 16, Folder 222)
    - "Introduction to Animal Happiness (Rights In, Of and For Animals){Why Dogs Bark at Mailmen}," draft, typescript, 1991 (Box 16, Folder 223)
    - "Introduction to Toto," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 16, Folder 224)
    - "Irish Bull Terriers and Their Friends," partial draft, typescript, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 225)
    - "Job's Animals: An Admonition," offprint of article published in Common Knowledge, undated (Box 16, Folder 226)
    - "Job's Animals: Reflections on the Sacred and the Ordinary: Literature, Animals and Ethics: Literature Doesn't Vote," with header, "Springfield Job," draft, typescript, 1993 Nov 4; accompanied by typescripts of poems from "Between Fences" and a holograph note in an unidentified hand (Box 16, Folder 227)
    - "Lo, Hear the Gentle Pit Bull! Real Love Has Teeth," printed version, published in Harper's magazine, 1985 June (Box 16, Folder 228)
    - "Me and My Consciousness," printed version, published in Zirkus, the Yale Literary Journal, 1986 Spring (Box 16, Folder 229)
    - "Men and Women and Animals," two drafts, typescript, 1989 (Box 16, Folder 230)
    - "Misleading Advertising," draft, typescript, undated (Box 16, Folder 231)
    - "The Moral Transformation of the Dog," printed version, published in Harper's, 1984 January (Box 16, Folder 232)
    - "Muzzles and Rumours," draft, typescript (photocopy), corrected with holograph note, undated (Box 16, Folder 233)
    - "Obediant [sic] 'N Brave: A Speculative Booke on the Nature of the Working Animal," draft, holograph, in notebook, accompanied by notes and mimeographed typescript poems by various authors, undated (Box 16, Folder 234)
    - "'On the Turf,' For Example," draft, typescript (original and photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 17, Folder 235)
    - "Only in America," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 17, Folder 236)
    - "Ornery," multiple drafts, typescript, 2000 (Box 17, Folder 237-238)
    - "Pete the Pup Meets the City Council," two drafts, typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 239)
    - "The Problem of Belief: An Open Letter to Philosophy," four drafts, typescript, corrected; one draft accompanied by photocopied drafts of "The Problem of Belief" by Hearne and Robert Tragesser, and "The Domain of Reference", undated (Box 17, Folder 240-241)
    - "Protection for Companion Dogs," draft, typescript, with cover letter to Chairman of The American Kennel Club dated 2/23/1986 (Box 17, Folder 242)
    - "The Question of Animal Rights," draft, typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 243)
    - "Reflections (Questions about Language): I. Horses, II. Cats" printed versions, published in Harper's magazine, 1986 Aug 18 and Aug 25 (Box 17, Folder 244)
    - "Revision," draft, typescript, undated (Box 17, Folder 245)
    - "Something Funny About That Dog," multiple drafts, typescript, corrected, 2000, undated (Box 17, Folder 246-248)
    - "The Sound of Kindness and Why It Matters: A Feminist Position Paper," three drafts, typescript, corrected, one annotated with cover letter from "Dick" discussing his annotations, 1985, undated (Box 17, Folder 249)
    - "Talking with Dogs, Chimps, and Others," proof, (photocopy), corrected, for Harper's magazine, [1984] (Box 17, Folder 250)
    - "Talking with Dogs, Chimps, and Others," photocopy of printed version, published in Raritan, 1982 Summer (Box 17, Folder 251)
    - "There's a Pit Bull in Your Town, Mister: A Criticism of Kindness," draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 17, Folder 252)
    - "The Thoroughbred Mutt," draft, typescript, corrected, 1991 (Box 17, Folder 253)
    - "Tracking Dogs and the Traces of Speech," draft, typescript with drawing, (photocopy), undated (Box 17, Folder 254)
    - "Welcome to the Real World, Shirley Anne," two drafts, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 17, Folder 255)
    - "What Is His Name?," draft, typescript, accompanied by copy of cover letter to Nelson Aldrich of Lears Magazine with holograph note to "Bob", 1991 (Box 18, Folder 256)
    - "What Teaching Dogs Teaches Us," printed version, published in New Scientist, 1982 March 12 (Box 18, Folder 257)
    - "What's Wrong with Animal Rights," printed version, published in Harper's magazine, 1991 September (Box 18, Folder 258)
    - "Will the Real Animal Lovers Please Stand Up? Project X and the Question of Rin Tin Tin," draft, typescript, "3rd draft", undated (Box 18, Folder 259)
    - "Will the Real Animal Lovers Please Stand Up? Reflections on the Sacred and the Ordinary," annotated typescript, 1990 (Box 18, Folder 260)
    - "The Wrath of Intellect, the Wrath of God," draft, holograph in notebook with other notes and writings; an essay on animal rights and animal welfare laid in, undated (Box 18, Folder 261)
  - Book Reviews
    - Review of Animal Thinking by Donald Griffin, drafts, typescripts (original and photocopy) corrected, entitled "Animal Made out of Words," and "Learning from the Birds and the Bees", undated (Box 18, Folder 262)
    - Review of Animal Thinking by Donald Griffin, printed version, published as "Talking Ants and Other Unorthodoxies," in The New York Times Book Review, 1984 May 27 (Box 18, Folder 263)
    - Review of The Eye of the Elephant by Delia Owens and Mark Owens and The Fate of the Elephant by Douglas H. Chadwick, printed version, published as "Wise Men and Elephants," in The New York Times Book Review, 1993 February 21 (Box 18, Folder 264)
    - Review of Through a Window: My Thirty Years with the Chimpanzees of Gombe, printed version, published as "Still Monkeying Around" in The New York Times Book Review, 1990 October 28 (Box 18, Folder 265)
  - Short Stories and Plays
    - "Bittersweet," draft, holograph in notebook with miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 266)
    - "Faking It," draft, manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 18, Folder 267)
    - "Fido: Play in 3 Strophes," draft, manuscript and typescript, corrected, undated (Box 18, Folder 268)
    - "In This Motion," draft, typescript, with editor's annotations, accompanied by photocopied typescript of "The Spine of Eclipse", undated (Box 18, Folder 269)
    - Folder labeled "In This Motion" containing short stories, undated (Box 18, Folder 270)
      "The Point of the Story," draft, typescript (photocopy), corrected; "Shirley Anne's Triumph," draft, typescript, corrected; "The Spine of Eclipse,"draft, typescript (photocopy); "Without Offense to Thyself or Thy Beast," draft, typescript (original and photocopy)
    - "A New Principle in Southern California," two drafts, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 18, Folder 271)
    - "The Problem of Belief," (co-authored by Robert Tragesser) drafts, typescript, (original and photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 19, Folder 272-280)
    - "Spine of Eclipse"
      - "Old version," draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 19, Folder 281)
      - Draft, typescript (photocopy), with editor's annotations, 1994 (Box 19, Folder 282)
      - Multiple drafts, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 19, Folder 283-289)
      - Multiple drafts, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 20, Folder 290-293)
    - "Under the Bamboo Tree," draft, holograph in notebook, undated (Box 20, Folder 294)
    - Untitled short story, draft, typescript, corrected, accompanied by the poem, "A Matter of Clarification," typescript carbon, undated (Box 20, Folder 295)
    - "When God Thinks," drafts, typescript (original and photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 20, Folder 296)
  - Poetry
    - Collections
      - "Between Fences," three drafts, typescript, undated (Box 20, Folder 297-299)
        General note
        Poems from this collection were published in Hearne's The Parts of Light (1994)
      - In the Absence of Horses
        - Draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 20, Folder 300)
        - Review from The Threepenny Review, 1985 (Box 20, Folder 301)
      - "Intermediate Philosophy," draft, holograph and typescript, in binder with poems for "Some General Principles on the Art of Riding," and others, undated (Box 21, Folder 302-303)
      - Nervous Horses
        - "Riding a Nervous Horse," mock up of volume of poetry with illustrations by Katrin Wiese; accompanied by additional illustrations, 1977 (Box 21, Folder 304)
        - Multiple drafts, typescripts (original and photocopy) collection of poetry; some with illustrations by Katrin Wiese, undated (Box 21, Folder 305-310)
      - "On the Edge," draft, bound typescript, corrected, with miscellaneous holograph and typescript poems and essays, an undated letter draft to Sara, and a photograph of a dog and cat laid in (Box 22, Folder 311-312)
      - "Poems," draft, typescript (original and photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 22, Folder 313)
      - "The Purebred Dog Gazette," three drafts, typescript (original and photocopy), with paste-up illustrations, undated (Box 22, Folder 314-316)
      - "The Runner and the Mountain," draft, holograph and typescript, corrected, 1984 (Box 22, Folder 317)
      - "Some General Principles of the Art of Riding"
        - Multiple drafts, undated (Box 22, Folder 318-321)
        - Multiple drafts, accompanied by drafts of additional poems, undated (Box 23, Folder 322-326)
      - "Tricks of the Light"
        - Titled poems
          - Draft, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 327)
          - Draft, typescript in envelope marked "for Petilos", undated (Box 23, Folder 328)
        - Poems in numbered parts
          - Parts I-V, two drafts, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 329-330)
          - Parts I-V, draft, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 23, Folder 331)
          - Parts I-V (missing first page) and titled poems with title, "Tricks of the Kight [sic]", drafts, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 332-333)
          - Parts I and II with footer "Tricks of the Light: New and Selected Poems" and Part V, draft, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 334)
        - Poems with titles and in numbered parts, draft, typescript, undated (Box 23, Folder 335)
    - Individual Poems
      - "Advent 1998," multiple drafts (Box 24, Folder 336)
      - "Before the War," with "A Brief Introduction to Vicki Hearne" by Richard Maxwell, printed version, published in The Cresset, 1993 March (Box 24, Folder 337)
      - "The Figure 1," multiple drafts, 1989, undated (Box 24, Folder 338)
      - "Letter to a Philosopher," and "Philosophy," draft, typescript, undated (Box 24, Folder 339)
      - "Lux et Veritas," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 340)
      - "On R.L.S. and Happiness," and "The Claim of Speech," printed version, published in Poetry, 1981 August (Box 24, Folder 341)
      - "A Poet's Sampler," printed version, published in Boston Review, 1991 April (Box 24, Folder 342)
      - "The Runner and the Mountain," printed version, published in The New Republic, 1991 January 7, 14 (Box 24, Folder 343)
      - "To My Husband, To Make Much of Time," printed version, published (under her married name Victoria Lerman) in Poetry UCR, 1969 Spring (Box 24, Folder 344)
      - "We Are Building a Garden," and "Even Thoreau Must Go," drafts, typescript and mimeograph, 1994, undated (Box 24, Folder 345)
    - Other Poems
      - Poems about Israel, with letter to "Ed," draft, holograph, undated (Box 24, Folder 346)
      - "Poems, summer 1970, VHL," draft, typescript, corrected (Box 24, Folder 347)
      - "Exercises, etc.," draft, typescript (original and photocopy), corrected, undated (Box 24, Folder 348)
      - "Work in Progress" files, 2001 (Box 24, Folder 349-351)
      - "Some others", 1999-2001, undated (Box 24, Folder 352-354)
      - Miscellaneous drafts, 1975-1986, undated (Box 24, Folder 355-361)
      - Miscellaneous drafts, 1975-1986, undated (Box 25, Folder 362-369)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - Foldered miscellaneous writings
      - Partial and complete typescript drafts of essays and poems, 1991, undated (Box 25, Folder 370)
        "The Airedale: The Case of Genial Fraud"; "Oyez a Beaumont" "Harry" "The Poetry of Everyday Life" (photocopy); "The Story of Old Drum"; "What Is His Name?"; "Thurber"; "Found Steel"
      - " Misc. notes, mostly on training," including holograph and typescript essays on Washoe and fetching, undated (Box 25, Folder 371)
      - Fragments, undated (Box 25, Folder 372-377)
    - Writings from loose-leaf binders
      - [Binder 1] Holograph and typescript drafts with corrections, 1983-1984, undated (Box 25, Folder 378)
        [ "The Domain of Reference"]; A proposal for the study of Stubbs Animal trainers;"Tracking Dogs and the Traces of Speech"; "Approaches to Chimera"; "The Axiom of Contradiction"; "The Annie Diary," holograph and typescript diary with various entries dating between 1983 Sep. 9 and "Xmas eve, 1983," with notes
        Letter, typescript, to Ruth Marcus, 1984 Feb 14
        Astrological chart, holograh, undated
      - [Binder 2] Holograph and typescript drafts, etc., 2001, undated (Box 25, Folder 379)
        Mathematical equations, holograph; "The Dog Purges," holograph essay; "The New Tree, On the Occasion of the Achievement of Breath of Daniel," typescript poem; Fax from Maureen Dillon to Vicki Hearne 2001 Aug. 7, wanting two-page attachment; Short essay on a tabby cat, holograph; Snapshot photographs of Vicki Hearne; Blank envelopes with postage affixed
      - [Binder 3] Draft of a book on animal training containing holograph and typescript essays and notes arranged by chapter/sections, undated (Box 26, Folder 380-382)
        "Introductory"; "The Working Animal: Some Preliminary Considerations"; "Chapter I: Domestic, Tame, Feral, and Wild"; "Obedience"; "Examples"; "Imitation of Nature"; "The Zipless Retrieve: A Dog Trainer's Theory of Natural Selection"; "Right and Wrong"; "Harshness" and "Cruelty"; "Legal Protection for Companion Dogs?"; Holograph table of contents; "A Plea for Anthropomorphism"; "No Proper Dogs"
      - [Binder 4] Holograph and typescript drafts, undated (Box 26, Folder 383-386)
        Untitled collection of poems by Hearne with table of contents, holograph and typescript; Spiral-bound notebook containing research notes chiefly on dog training; Comments by Randall Havas on the "Rockville, Maryland Off-Leash with Permission program," typescript
        Material arranged in the following categories: "Verse in progress," typescript and holograph poems by Hearne, "Reference," typescript drafts with corrections of "The Domain of Reference", "Police Dogs" typescript drafts with corrections of "The Book of Justice: the Chapter on Dogs", Miscellaneous poems
      - [Binder 5] Holograph and typescript drafts, etc., 1998-2000, undated (Box 26, Folder 387-389)
        Photographic slides of a donkey, horse, and unidentified man
        "Ornery," draft, typescript, corrected, 2000 Jun 11
        Yale spiral notebook with holograph title, "Gallantry to Life," containing essays on cats, 2000 May 5
        Yale spiral notebook with holograph title, "Canis Lupis Familiaris," containing draft of "Something Funny About That Dog;" draft of "Why Train;" notes on dogs and wolves; and drafts of letters: to Wendy, 2000 Sept 25, and to Professor Margulis, n.d.
        Photocopies of articles and information from publications and Web sites on endangered species legislation, animal welfare, and molecular evolution of the dog, 1993, 1998, 1999
      - [Binder 5] Holograph and typescript drafts, etc., 1998-2000, undated (Box 27, Folder 390-394)
      - [Binder 6], Day Runner binder containing miscellaneous holograph writings and notes, undated (Box 27, Folder 395)
    - Spiral-bound notebooks
      - Writings, general
        - Drafts of letters and miscellaneous writings, 1989-1990 (Box 27, Folder 396)
        - Research notes, writings on rhetoric, draft of letter, with typescript writings and holograph notes laid in, undated (Box 27, Folder 397)
        - Miscellaneous writings and draft of letter to "Bill," dated 1981 Mar 15, 1981, undated (Box 27, Folder 398)
        - Miscellaneous writings and notes, undated (Box 28, Folder 399-406)
      - Poems
        - Poems and notes on horse anatomy, undated (Box 29, Folder 407-408)
        - Poems and notes on horse training, undated (Box 29, Folder 409)
        - Poems and miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 29, Folder 410-416)
        - Poems and miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 30, Folder 417-426)
        - Poems and miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 31, Folder 427-437)
      - Notes, etc.
        - Animal behavior, undated (Box 32, Folder 438)
        - Animal rights, undated (Box 32, Folder 439)
        - Dog laws, undated (Box 32, Folder 440)
        - Horse anatomy, undated (Box 32, Folder 441-442)
        - National horse show, [circa 1985] (Box 32, Folder 443)
        - Philosophy, undated (Box 32, Folder 444)
        - Various writings and notes with draft of letter to "Joan," dated 1985 Jan 11, 1985 January 11, undated (Box 32, Folder 445)
        - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 33, Folder 446-453)
        - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 34, Folder 454-463)
        - Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 35, Folder 464-469)
    - Teaching files
      - Notes for a lecture on rhetoric, typescript and holograph, undated (Box 35, Folder 470)
      - Lecture notes for "Rota's class," typescript, 1997 (Box 35, Folder 471)
      - Handouts for creative writing class, typescript, mimeographed, 1981 (Box 35, Folder 472)
  - Writings of Others
    - Bloom, Harold: Introduction to Vicki Hearne's poetry, holograph, undated (Box 36, Folder 473)
    - Borges, Jorge Luis: In Praise of Darkness, photocopied pages from publication, 1974 (Box 36, Folder 474)
    - Dayan, Joan: "The Analytic of the Dash: Poe's Eureka," offprint from Genre, 1983 (Box 36, Folder 475)
    - Frasher, John: "In Defence of Culture: Huckleberry Finn, offprint (photocopy) from Oxford Review, 1968 (Box 36, Folder 476)
    - Hanna, Robert: Review of Ethics and the Limits of Philosophy by Bernard Williams, typescript, [1986] (Box 36, Folder 477)
    - Hollander, John: "Powers of Thirteen," typescript (photocopy), bound, with inscription to Hearne, undated (Box 36, Folder 478)
    - McCaig, Donald: Commentaries written for National Public Radio programs, typescript, and magazine and newspaper article clippings, 1993-1994, undated (Box 36, Folder 479)
    - Miller, Milton: "Hamaguchi: A Libretto," draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 36, Folder 480)
    - Schroeder, Bethany: Poems, typescripts, [1982-1984?] (Box 36, Folder 481)
    - Tragesser, Robert S.
      - "Discourse Warping and The Origin of Almost Everything (An Essay on the Problem of Truth in Our Times)," two drafts, typescript (photocopy), corrected and annotated, 1982 (Box 36, Folder 482)
      - "Some Observations Concerning Logics and Concepts of Existence," offprint from The Journal of Philosophy, [1972] (Box 36, Folder 483)
    - Unidentified: "Who Will Protest", draft, typescript (photocopy), undated (Box 36, Folder 484)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 36, Folder 485)
- Animal Records and Training Files, 1989-2001; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  Arranged by type of material.
  The majority of material in this series consists of registrations and certificates for Hearne's companion animals. A small group of materials relates to dog training and information on various dog breeds and animal behavior. The material dates from 1989 to 2001.
  - Registrations and certificates, 1989-1998 (Box 37, Folder 486-490)
    Contains dog club registrations, obedience title certificates, and obedience trial ribbons; town registration and rabies certificates, and veterinary records.
  - Show ribbons, undated (Box 37, Folder 491)
  - "The Obedience Method of Rebreaking and Rebalancing," typescript of a course outline, 1989 (Box 37, Folder 492)
  - Waivers for obedience class taught by Hearne, 1989 (Box 37, Folder 493)
  - Breed information, 1996, 1999, undated (Box 37, Folder 494)
  - Miscellaneous photocopies of published articles on animal behavior, 1993, 2001, undated (Box 37, Folder 495)
- Personal Papers, 1920-2001; Series IV; 0.83; (2 boxes)
  This series consists of a small number of legal, financial and medical documents, including Hearne's brief will; personal writings including a school notebook and notes relating to her illness; newspaper and magazine articles about, and interviews with, Hearne; two posters advertising Hearne readings; drawings by Katrin Wiese, sketchbooks containing drawings by unidentified artist(s), and miscellaneous publications and ephemera. The bulk of the material dates from 1968 to 2001.
  - Legal and financial documents, 1986, 2001 (Box 38, Folder 496)
  - Medical records, 1976-1992 (Box 38, Folder 497)
  - Spiral notebooks
    - "Literature Notebook" from a junior high school English class, 1968 (Box 38, Folder 498)